software engineering radio episode 11
interview with Gregor kiss Alice
[Music]
hi everybody and welcome to this new
episode of software engineering radio
this is another interview episode and
this time we have the great pleasure of
interviewing Gregor Casillas he's one of
the fathers of aspect-oriented
programming back in the days when he was
still at Xerox PARC he and other folks
worked on aspect-oriented programming as
well as on some of the forerunners for
example meta object protocols
he's also co-author of a book called the
art of the metal object protocol where
he and his co-authors explained how many
object protocols work this is really
interesting reading today he's a
professor at the University of British
Columbia in Vancouver I met Gregor at
the AOS D 2006 conference in Bonn
Germany note that we had some kind of a
problem of finding a quiet spot in the
conference when you saw the sound
quality is not always that good
so welcome Gregor to this show why don't
you explain your personal background and
your involvement in aspect-oriented
software development I thank you very
much
it's a pleasure to be here I guess my
work on aspects goes back it goes back
quite a ways we in some sense we started
working on some of the precursor ideas
when we were working with reflection and
meta object protocols even and even in
the mid 80s and and then in different
ways that work led us to start working
on the idea that we now call aspect
oriented programming through the mid 90s
and and up right up until today so if we
look at the history specifically metal
object protocols and stuff but what is
the relation between the two some is
obviously more dynamic the others more
static typically at least so how do you
see or how do you explain how would you
see how one developed from the other
what's the relationship there well with
meta object protocols there were really
a lot of different things going on three
in particular is that with meta object
protocols you have you have language
extensibility you have meta level shift
which is which is more intellectually
interesting than
at least in the context of meta object
protocols is primarily intellectually
interesting and you also have modular
modular implementation of cross-cutting
concerns and I think when we were
winding down the work with meta object
protocols and starting to look at some
of the problems with making larger fix
efficient flexible systems we really
started to focus on you know which of
those properties of an object protocols
was doing the most work for us I think
that's when we really began to focus on
on this notion of modular cross-cutting
at the time that we did the metallurgic
Protocol work we didn't call it modular
cross-cutting but we really I think and
this was in the period sort of in the
early 90s mid 90s really came to
understand that that this notion of
cross-cutting structure and modular
cross-cutting structure was was
important and then with AOP I think that
what we did was to really focus on that
and in particular a opie languages like
aspectj give you give you the ability to
modular eyes cross-cutting concerns
without having any metal level shift and
without having language extensibility
they really focus on that on that
particular issue so some people say
maybe the more critical people say that
aspect orientation is something that has
been there a long time it has just been
called using interceptors or using
proxies factories and interceptors so
how do you see the relationship there is
is AOP to some extent kind of
refurbished interceptor thing or our
interceptors an instance of the more
general AOP or a OSD thing well I mean
that's a good question I think it's
actually several good questions um you
know I mean one question is is is
interceptor based programming AOP
programming and another kind of question
is you know which came first I think the
first question is is in some sense more
interesting you know I mean the main
problem of any or the main goal of any
programming technology is to solve
problems and to make systems in some way
higher quality make them make them run
faster make them cheaper to develop make
them more fun to develop make them
more configurable solve some real
problem so I mean the first thing to say
about Interceptor based technology if
it's is it is that it fin a particular
system it solves the problem that you
need solving then and that's what
matters that said I think that one way
of looking at using interceptors is that
it provides you a kind of coarse-grained
version of the same kind of
functionality that you get with point
cuts and advice in a language like
aspectj so there's a similarity there
but but each of those words in that
sentence is carefully chosen
it's coarse-grained in the sense that
with with the point cuts of an advice of
a language like aspectj
you get much more fine-grained join
point model and the ability to cross cut
things at a much more fine grained level
the other thing that you get you know in
a language like a spec J's you have a
linguistic model for it so you get all
kinds of composition properties that you
don't get in most interceptor based
approaches and you can also get things
like static checking and and radically
more efficiency than you get in an
interceptor based approach so so I think
what you see is that you know maybe one
way of thinking of it is that people use
interceptors to do a kind of ad hoc
version of of handling cross-cutting
concerns and if that's good enough for
the problem at hand then that's good
enough for the problem at hand and then
people who have problems that require
sort of a more systematic use of modular
izing cross-cutting concerns are going
to need to go to a more systematic and
well engineered set a sort of tool and
maybe that's going to look less
interceptor based there is this question
whether you might think that AOP is more
important on this finer fine-grained
level of programming languages where
also some people say this breaks and
capsulation therefore isn't good or
whether a opie is more important on an
architecture level so you use components
containers with interceptors and some
people say that's actually more valuable
because it's a more specifically defined
John point model basically instead of
being being able to mess around with
Java as some people might say so so do
you have an
piñon on that well I think it's
important to both levels and just in
different ways you know we could come
back to the encapsulation question later
I think that if you look for example at
the way AOP works in something like the
Spring Framework
you've got relatively coarse level you
know it works on the container invoke
calls and they get a tremendous amount
of value out of that I think if you look
at the way that some people program with
aspectj
where they write very fine-grained
boycotts or they you know they write a
point cut that matches against a million
lines of code that somebody else wrote
and that solves a problem for them so
you know I I just don't think it's um I
just don't think the way to look at it
is whether it's more important in one
domain or the other it's important in
both domains to deal with cross-cutting
concerns I mean I think the real
contribution of of Victorian programming
you know 10 or 15 or 20 years from now
is going to be that we gave a name to a
problem that had been around for a long
time but but a community of people you
know the the people working that I was
working with it parked but also many
other people you know collectively
finally got clarity on this problem of
cross-cutting concerns and that problem
happens at all sorts of different scales
and in all sorts of different systems
and like any other such problem there's
going to be different technical
solutions to it in its different forms
so I really think the main issue here is
coping with cross-cutting concerns in a
modular way and a language like aspectj
does that very well in at certain levels
of granularity and something like the
spring AOP framework does it very well
at other levels of granularity and I
think we're gonna see much more macro
versions of the technology as well as we
come to understand it better so do you
want to come back to the breaking the
encapsulation thing that some critics
I mean you've probably asked answer that
5 million times but just to just for
completeness okay so so the you know the
AOP breaks modularity question
I mean my answer to that is simple it
doesn't it not only doesn't break
modularity it improves modularity now so
the question is why is it that that
people can say that it does break
modularity and I can say that it not
that it doesn't break modularity and
let's just stipulate that neither of us
is crazy the answer really is that the
existing kinds of modularity enforcement
mechanisms the encapsulation mechanisms
mechanisms we have technically they do
the job that we say they do but if you
look at what actually happens in
software practice the current mechanisms
force people to go around them all the
time
so we've shown in a number of examples
there's a for people who like to read
this kind of academic paper there's a
paper that I wrote with a colleague
mirror Mazzini
from Darmstadt in which we basically
showed that for a very simple example
what will happen is that the developer
will have to go around the modularity
mechanism and go scatter code all around
so you can say that the old modularity
mechanism enforced modularity but the
social practice went around it and so
what AOP in some sense is doing is it's
trying to be true to what's actually
happening I think that was one of the
fundamental fundamental things that we
at least were working with in the group
at Parc you know we were sitting there
at Parc down the hallway from the
ethnographers and and hearing them say
look it's not enough to just listen to
the story people tell about technology
you have to go see what's actually
happening in practice and I think that's
part of what's helped us get this
insight that you know you can tell me
that Java provides strict encapsulation
but if what all the programmers are
doing is violating that encapsulation
then in fact it's not really doing the
thing you say and I think if you look at
AOP programs you get a modularity that
is more natural and so the way people
are gonna work with it is gonna be more
natural you know that's why it's sort of
both people are right the old language
has had this modularity enforcement
hey Opie has a different modularity
enforcement mechanism but the old
languages weren't really giving you the
modularity that that they said because
people were sort of systematically
punching them in the nose all the time
so you already talked about the
practical relevance of a OSD or an AOP
so what do you think about the
acceptance of aspect-oriented
programming in 2006 by the industry is
it as you expected is it running better
as you might have wished or what's
what's your opinion of that I think it's
running incredibly much better than we
could possibly have expected right now
if you look at sort of the enterprise
Java space and you look at frameworks
like like J Boston spring you know the
fact that those frameworks are built in
part using aspects of course they use
lots of other technologies but the fact
that those frameworks are built in part
using aspect technology and then in fact
aspect technology is an important
component of how they're built you know
it's really quite incredible I mean well
I I don't have the exact numbers off the
top of my head but frameworks like JBoss
and spring have a huge number of users
you know big banks lots of big companies
I mean they're just standard development
technology and here they are using this
aspect stuff which depending on when you
want to say aspects started is less than
10 years old that's not the normal life
cycle of true innovations in software
development you know things that are
truly new things that are intellectually
controversial tend to take more like 20
years to work their way into standard
practice you know people will say well
no that's not true you know technical
innovations can be adopted very quickly
look at how quickly Java was adopted but
that's quite different right when Java
came in it was a sixth or seventh
generation of virtual machine based
object oriented programming language I'm
not detracting from from what Java what
is it all but it was not intellectually
controversial at the time that it came
in whereas as we were just talking about
with the encapsulation thing a opie was
intellectually controversial and still
is
so I just think that AOP is being
adopted incredibly quickly
clearly Enterprise Java is so far the
space where it's being adopted most
quickly but couldn't have imagined it
going more quickly and I don't think
anybody involved with it could have
imagined it going more quickly so so
some people say that modularizing
technical cross-cutting concerns like
persistence tracing the usual suspects
persistence is rather easy and has been
done all the time therefore aop is
nothing new and if you talk to more
expert AOP community members they will
tell you that a opie can and should also
be used to modularize cross-cutting
concerns in business logic so what do
you think the state of the art is there
is it kind of accepted practice in
industry to use AOP for business logic
modularization or is it still more or
less at this at this technical
cross-cutting
level well I think again if you look in
the enterprise Java space what's what's
most widely accepted is is to use is to
use aspect techniques for modularizing
what I like to call the big a aspects no
persistence logging of the generic
things now there's two reasons for that
one reason is people start by doing the
things for which there are a lot of
examples um you know when people first
saw systems like small talk you know the
first objects they made were always you
know things like windows and and things
that that moved around on the screen and
lines and points and circles and stuff
like that right in fact for a while
people used to think that what the
object metaphor meant was that it was
something that existed in the display on
the desktop another reason why that's
what people mostly do right now is that
is that frameworks like like spring
really are only supporting that kind of
aspect right there it's a very well
engineered framework for supporting
these coarse-grain aspects that was
really their design goal and so people
who start programming start programming
these aspects in that kind of context
they there's examples to do that and B
that's what the framework supports so
that's what they do
now if you look at what what people who
program with aspectj do they tend to
start writing aspects like that actually
they the most common scenarios start by
writing um debugging and architecture
enforcement aspects but then they
gradually move to writing aspects sort
of systematically throughout their
application wherever it makes most sense
you know so those end up in in core
business logic they end up wherever
there's a cross-cutting concern what
there's absolutely no doubt about is
that there are cross-cutting concerns
that are in in the business logic there
are cross-cutting concerns that have
very small range there are cross-cutting
concerns that are these so-called
technical or systemic things that have
very large range there's nothing about
the idea of cross-cutting that restricts
it to any particular kind of concern
it's not cross-cutting you know one of
the I think the most common
misconceptions about cross-cutting
is to try to equate it with something so
people will say well cross-cutting
concerns are the optional concerns
that's not true cross-cutting concerns
are the non-functional concerns that's
not true cross-cutting concerns are the
you know computer science II concerns
that's not true what cross-cutting
concerns are is there cross-cutting and
some of those things have cross-cutting
properties but lots of other things too
I am I'm actually writing a little
compiler right now in aspectj
and in the code generation phase the
code generator needs to make sure that
it's properly emitting code that
properly respects stack discipline and I
have a little aspect that Crosscut's the
entire code generator that just keeps
track of making sure that the generated
code enforces that properly respects the
stack doesn't once I could have written
that code in another way but when I
write it as an aspect it's a really
beautiful code and you know it's not a
it's not persistence it's not
synchronization it's not anything like
that it's a core part of making sure
that my compiler is generating correct
code so let's maybe briefly look at some
of the other hype technologies today one
is certainly scripting languages dynamic
languages
the other big thing currently certainly
model driven development approaches so
I'd like to
your opinion on how a OSD and IOP
specifically relates to this approach
some people say you don't need it in
Ruby because you just you know you
change something in the class definition
or you run to use runtime code
generation or some reflective means to
do the same stuff and some people say
that in model driven development
you don't need a o P because you can let
your generator handle some of the
cross-cutting aspects so do you have any
enlightenment on on these things well
again I mean I think the way to think
about the answer to these questions is
is to go back to the point I made that
that what's really important about AOPA
OSD is this focus on this notion that
there are cross-cutting concerns and
that there's a family of techniques for
modularizing them the so called join
point models now why am I going to that
level to answer your your question it
seems like I'm making the question more
complicated rather than simple but
actually here's why let's look at
modeling and let's look at a fairly
standard modeling modeling language you
know the UML and and simple things like
state charts and cost diagrams and
sequence diagrams when you take the
perspective of cross-cutting concerns
and joint point models to modularize
them what you immediately see is that
one of the reasons why the combination
of class diagrams sequence diagrams and
state charts is such a powerful tool in
UML is that in fact those three diagrams
cross cut each other the combination of
the three diagrams allows you to
modularize important kinds of
cross-cutting concerns at the model
level so what that says is and this is
should not come as a great surprise is
that there were already ad hoc solutions
to parts of the problem of coping with
cross-cutting concerns and we knew that
what it also says and we've done this as
a as a project at UBC is that you can
reconstruct the kinds of mechanisms that
exist in things like the UML explicitly
a notion in terms of joint point models
and you actually get a little bit of
additional power there
so you know so the question is you know
the question well you don't need a specs
if you're doing modeling I just don't
think that's right I think what what is
the case is that modeling tools already
have aspect like functionality in them
and by recognizing that from both
perspectives both from the aspect camp
and the modeling camp we can just do a
better job of achieving modularity at
the model level I think it's also fairly
clear that there will be times when you
want your modeling tool to generate code
in an AOP language and there will be
times when you don't want your your code
your modeling tool to generate code in
an AOP language as you can see I mean I
try to avoid giving sort of categorical
answers because I think that that all
these things are really engineering
decisions and that engineers have to
make the right decision at the right
time and and I don't like the way so
much of the way technical stuff these
days is sort of ends up being hyped as
the ultimate solution none of these
things are the ultimate solution but all
of them used together can be very
powerful solutions when you use the
right one at the right time yesterday in
a workshop here at the ASD conference we
took several notes on the flip chart and
one of it was it said think AOP which we
kind of said it's more important than
use a Oh programming language is hearing
or listening to what you're saying you
would probably agree to that I'm not
sure I think it's more important but I
think it's as important certainly one
adoption paradigm for aspects is to
think aspects and still write
old-fashioned code one of the things
that that a number of us have advised
people to do is if you go you hear a
lecture about aspect or any programming
and you come away excited but you can't
change your programming language today
there is a thing you can do which is
that you can you can realize hey I'm
struggling with a cross-cutting concern
here and you can write some pseudo
aspectj code in a comment and then you
can go scatter that code manually and
yes in some sense your code is no better
than it used to be because it's still
scattered and tangled
but in fact it is much better because
now there is a crisp definition of how
it got scattered and actually if you go
back to sort of the early days of the
object idea what a lot of people did is
they saw the object idea but they didn't
have a language and they just started
programming little vectors of methods
that they passed around and that was
kind of like something they were already
doing but because they now had an or an
intellectual idea with which to organize
it they did it in a little bit more
disciplined away a little bit more
principled away and their code got
better so I think you can I think if
you're going to program in aspects you
absolutely have to think in aspects and
I think that if you if you can't program
with an AOP language you can get a lot
of benefit by just thinking in terms of
aspects certainly what's true is you
know really get your head around this
stuff you know it is going to take some
time thinking in terms of it so you can
start before you start programming in
terms of it so to kind of sum up the the
practical discussion about the practical
aspects of ILP are there any
standardization efforts for a old
languages obviously this is probably
then specific to the base language so is
there anything standardization efforts
for for example various Java ao
extensions or other standardization
efforts in other languages well I think
on the Java side what you're seeing is
sort of a de-facto standardization
process that's emerging seven years ago
we had one language aspectj
and you know three years ago we had a
three or four important tools there was
a spec Jay that was aspect works there
was the spring AOP framework and the
JBoss AOP framework you know today what
we've seen is that aspect works has has
merged and merged back into aspectj and
now spring the lead developer of the
aspectj project now works for interface
21 the company that supports spring so
spring is has the plan to continue to
use its own framework for the
coarse-grain aspect stuff and to and to
begin using aspectj
for fine-grained aspects stuff
so really you've got kind of IBM be EA
and spraying on top of aspectj and and
and the spring framework so I think
there's a pretty strong de-facto
standardization there all of that seems
to really be driving in the aspectj
direction on the.net platform I don't
think there is yet a clear you know a
clear de facto standard there that's
sort of a different platform because at
the end of the day you know Microsoft is
going to have to make a move you know
there's some rumbling with that that
that is at least beginning to be thought
about my personal opinion is that it's
too soon to even think about something
like a jsr for AOP like functionality
and aspect in in java when you've got a
strong enough to facto standard but you
still have a little bit of competition
in the space I think that's good for the
technology I don't see the need to put
it in a jsr that that would not have you
know that would make it difficult to
improve over the next three or four
years at this point I don't hear people
say that the reason they're not adopting
AOP is that there's not a clear standard
I'm sure that's true for some people but
at this stage of the adoption cycle I
don't think that's a dominant factor and
so I personally would not encourage
something like a jsr or encourage other
people to do so but at some point down
the road something like that's going to
happen so since we were at yeah more or
less research conference here at the AOS
D conference 2006 in Bonn Germany I
think we should do some kind of
excursion into the research part of ALP
there are various interesting things
going on here for example what many
people call early aspects so that means
using a techniques in development phases
before implementation so this includes
design modeling refactor at refactoring
requirements and these kinds of things
can you give us a little overview of
what's going on there and then maybe
we're a opie research focuses these days
I mean I think what you're seeing is is
you know at this point we as a research
community just understand a lot more
about what it means for
software technology to be mature and and
so you see people trying to move much
more quickly from kind of just having a
programming language to having design
design tools and having design methods
and having verification techniques and
having testing techniques and all the
way to having you know requirements and
analysis techniques and so what
researchers who specialized in each of
those subfields are doing is they're
sort of trying to look at this idea of
modular cross-cutting through joint
point models and understand how it plays
in their space since we started with
programming languages you know clearly
the programming language work is is the
farthest ahead it's the stuff that's
most production ready but but these
other areas of work are coming along
tremendously fast and and the the the
vendors or at least the big vendors are
being asked by their customers for
answers to some of these problems and I
think when some of the researchers are
hearing from from companies that fund
research is you know a real interest in
in answers to some of these problems so
really you know there's just great
research going on right now in all of
those earlier stages of the lifecycle
and in working with aspects like ideas
and I think we're gonna we're gonna see
tools methods processes and and
techniques come out of all that that
will be useful for people that work that
way in the near future so again for the
practitioners which is probably most of
our listeners do we have some best
practices of how to pragmatically adopt
AOP in in in projects I mean let's
assume we have an io language like a
spec J and we are allowed to use it by
our I don't know central IT strategy
department so what's the best process
how should people go about approaching
introducing AOP yeah actually I mean I
do have an answer to that and and the
answer actually starts by not assuming
that you have approval to do so what
we've done actually is that sort of kind
of a consortium of the leading
consultants in in the aspect technology
space have really agreed with each other
to
to adopt a strategy of of trying as much
as possible to not over hype the
technology and to encourage people to go
slowly and so we kind of have this this
three or four step process it depends a
bit on exactly how you break it down but
the first step is is to do what we call
development aspects and what development
aspects mean is that you use them on
your desktop and they don't get
committed to the main projects code
repository so development aspects
include things like your private tracing
aspects your private performance
monitoring aspects your private
debugging aspects things like that and
they also include architecture
enforcement aspects architecture
enforcement aspects are things that lets
you sort of do things like define a
certain layered architecture for your
system and use aspect technology to
ensure that you follow that architecture
what's important about development
aspects is is two things or I guess
three things one is they're easy to
start incrementally two is they're not
committed to the main code repository
they don't ship in the running code so
they have what what we call the you
could use them without telling your boss
property or more importantly they have
the you can use them without telling the
build manager property and what's
important about this is it means that
you can spend a month or two or three
however long it takes to really start to
understand the potential value of
aspects in your product before you have
to take on the challenge of convincing
somebody else
hey we should use this in the product
because otherwise you wind up in one of
these impossible conversations where you
say hey you know I read this great
article about this aspect technology we
should use it and your boss says what's
it going to do for us and you say I read
this great article about aspect
technology we should use it right I mean
your boss wants to know what's it going
to do for you and so if you take this
first adoption step you can really start
to get answers to that question before
trying to convince people and then what
happens in the second adoption step is
you you have just a few developers
programming with aspects and they're
writing those
infrastructure aspects things like
persistence and logging insecurity and
dot dot and so you're starting to spread
it out and the aspect ship in the
product but you've still restricted it
to a subpart of the development team and
then in the third stage is really when
you start to sort of let aspects be used
wherever in the business logic makes
most sense and what we found is that
people who follow this incremental
process tend to be successful they're
AOP adoption tends to tends to be
successful they really reduce their risk
because if in the if you get partway
into that first stage and it's not
working for you then you know you you
drop the code you've written you throw
it away and yes you lost some time but
you haven't messed up the rest of the
codebase and that seems to be really
important the other thing we find is
that when we tell people to follow this
process they all say okay yeah we'll do
that and we'll we'll do three months in
the first phase and six months in the
second phase and then we'll go to the
third phase and they all end up going
faster but having this stage process
seems to be important and if you look at
a lot of things that people have written
on their blogs like like Adrienne
Colliers blog or or the IBM
developerworks AOP at work series they
detail this process in much more detail
there's a very good article in that
series about this staged adoption
process okay and we'll put some of those
links into the show notes so you can
easily find them okay that wraps up my
questions and since we can't have
listener questions interactively
obviously for these reasons so click or
anything else you want to add to to kind
of I don't know clarify something that
you always wanted to say or anything
else about AOS team well no I would just
say I guess thanks for listening and you
know try this stuff out it's fun it
makes your code look good
and and at the end of the day you know
good looking code that does what it's
supposed to do and it's flexible and
it's fun to write is a good thing okay
thank you
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Hanning poly for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]